Hrishikesh Rajesh Terdalkar

A hrishikeshrt.github.io | In hrishikeshrt | O hrishikeshrt

+91 512 259 7579

hrishirt@cse.iitk.ac.in

SUMMARY

I am a dedicated **Natural Language Processing (NLP)** researcher with a passion for low-resource languages like **Sanskrit** and other **Indian languages**. My focus is on addressing the unique language challenges faced by these languages, enhancing language understanding, and advancing knowledge extraction from unstructured data. My research lies in the intersection of NLP, **Computational Linguistics**, and **Software Engineering**. I am committed to leveraging this interdisciplinary background to pioneer NLP innovations that have a strong real-world impact. My interests also encompass **Information Retrieval**, **Artificial Intelligence**, **Data Mining**, and **Machine Learning**.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering

Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

CGPA: 8.67

M.Sc. in Computer Science

Chennai Mathematical Institute

CGPA: 8.88

B.Sc. (Hons.) in Mathematics and Computer Science

Chennai Mathematical Institute

CGPA: 7.69

Higher Secondary School Certificate (Standard XII)

Maharashtra State Board of Secondary and Higher Secondary Education

Percentage: 86.50

Secondary School Certificate (Standard X)

Maharashtra State Board of Secondary and Higher Secondary Education

Percentage: 95.33

2014 – 2023* (under submission) Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh, India

2011 – 2013 Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India

2007 - 2010

Chennai, Tamil Nadu, India

2007

Pune, Maharashtra, India

2005 Pune, Maharashtra, India

THESES

Ph.D. Thesis

Sanskrit Knowledge-based Systems: Annotation and Computational Tools

Supervisor: Arnab Bhattacharya

- Development of knowledge-based systems in Sanskrit with the ultimate goal of question-answering in Sanskrit. Contributions include a framework for the automated construction of knowledge graphs; two web-based annotation tools: (1) Sangrahaka: for knowledge-graph focused annotation and querying, and (2) Antarlekhaka: for general purpose natural language annotation of multiple tasks in a sequential manner; a system to identify Sanskrit meters and utilize Sanskrit prosody for post-OCR correction; several web-interfaces including three ancient Indian alpha-numeric systems; tools including a Telegram bot for Sanskrit grammar, and software libraries related to computational aspects of Sanskrit.
- All contributions available at https://sanskrit.iitk.ac.in

M.Sc. Thesis Supervisor: Rajeeva Karandikar

On Symmetric Key Cryptography

Study and implementation of various stream ciphers and block ciphers. (RC4, HC128, RC5, IDEA).

PUBLICATIONS

- "Antarlekhaka: A Comprehensive Tool for Multi-task Natural Language Annotation". Hrishikesh Terdalkar, Arnab Bhattacharya. In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop for NLP Open Source Software (NLP-OSS) @ EMNLP, Singapore, December 2023. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL).
- "Chandojnanam: A Sanskrit Meter Identification and Utilization System". Hrishikesh Terdalkar, Arnab Bhattacharya. In Proceedings of the Computational Sanskrit & Digital Humanities: Selected papers presented at the 18th World Sanskrit Conference (WSC), pages 113–127, Canberra, Australia, January 2023. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL).

- "Semantic Annotation and Querying Framework based on Semi-structured Ayurvedic Text". **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Arnab Bhattacharya, Madhulika Dubey, Ramamurthy S, Bhavna Naneria Singh. In Proceedings of the Computational Sanskrit & Digital Humanities: Selected papers presented at the 18th World Sanskrit Conference (WSC), pages 155–173, Canberra, Australia, January 2023. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL).
- "A Novel Multi-Task Learning Approach for Context-Sensitive Compound Type Identification in Sanskrit". Jivnesh Sandhan, Ashish Gupta, **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Tushar Sandhan, Suvendu Samanta, Laxmidhar Behera, Pawan Goyal. In Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), pages 4071–4083, Gyeongju, Republic of Korea, October 2022. International Committee on Computational Linguistics.
- "Sangrahaka: A Tool for Annotating and Querying Knowledge Graphs". Hrishikesh Terdalkar, Arnab Bhattacharya. In Proceedings of the 29th ACM Joint Meeting on European Software Engineering Conference and Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (ESEC/FSE), pages 1520–1524, Athens, Greece, August 2021. Association for Computing Machinery (ACM).
- "Framework for Question-Answering in Sanskrit through Automated Construction of Knowledge Graphs".
 Hrishikesh Terdalkar, Arnab Bhattacharya. In Proceedings of the 6th International Sanskrit Computational Linguistics Symposium (ISCLS), pages 97–116, IIT Kharagpur, India, October 2019. Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL).

TALKS, POSTERS AND DEMONSTRATIONS

- "Āyurjñānam: Exploring Āyurvedawith Knowledge Graphs". Hrishikesh Terdalkar, Vishakha Deulgaonkar, Arnab Bhattacharya. National Youth Conference on Indian Knowledge Systems (NYCIKS), 2023.
 Best Poster Award.
- "Vaiyyākaraṇaḥ: A Sanskrit Grammar Bot for Telegram" . **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Mahesh A V S D S, Shubhangi Agarwal, Arnab Bhattacharya. The 18th World Sanskrit Conference (WSC), 2023.
- "PyCDSL: A Programmatic Interface to Cologne Digital Sanskrit Dictionaries". **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Arnab Bhattacharya. The 18th World Sanskrit Conference (WSC), 2023.
- "Jñānasaṅgrahaḥ: A Collection of Computational Applications related to Sanskrit" . **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Arnab Bhattacharya. The 18th World Sanskrit Conference (WSC), 2023.
- "KaTaPaYadi System". **Hrishikesh Terdalkar**, Arnab Bhattacharya. The 6th International Sanskrit Computational Linguistics Symposium (ISCLS), 2019.

EXPERIENCE

Student Researcher Aug 2022 – current

• Working in the project 'An Interpretable Unified Framework Text-to-text Translation among Indian Languages using Sanskrit-based Interlingua Representation', under Ministry of Electronics and Information Technology (MeitY), Government of India.

Student Researcher Jun 2022 – current

- Working in the project 'Automated Question-Answering System for Ramayana' under Indian Knowledge Systems (IKS) division of All India Council for Technical Education (AICTE), Government of India.
- Developing and maintaining a comprehensive NLP annotation tool Antarlekhaka.

Webmaster Jan 2023 – current

• Managing website for the conference ISCLS 2024.

External Reviewer 2020-2023

Cods-comad (2020, 2021, 2023), CIKM (2021, 2022), AAAI (2022), ARR (2022), DASFAA (2022)

Webmaster Dec 2014 – Jan 2016

• Managed website of CSE Department, IIT Kanpur.

Project Associate Jul 2013 – Apr 2014

• Worked on the project 'Localization in Wireless Sensor Networks' at CSE, IIT Kanpur.

Senior Tutor Jan 2017 - Nov 2020

- Managed (Prutor) backend administration for 5 semesters at IIT Kanpur.
- Duties also involved heading the tutor team, setting question papers and grading.

Teaching Assistant Aug 2014 - Nov 2020

- CS315: Principles of Database Systems (Jan-Apr 2019, Jan-Apr 2021)
- CS685: Data Mining (Aug-Nov 2018)
- CS774: Optimization Techniques (Aug-Nov 2016)
- ESC101: Introduction to Programming (Aug-Nov 2014)

Teaching Assistant (MOOC)

May 2017 - Sep 2017

NPTEL

NOC17-CS33: Fundamentals of Database Systems

ACHIEVEMENTS

- Best Poster Award at National Youth Conference on Indian Knowledge Systems 2023 NYCIKS 2023 (Roorkee).
- Financial support from Research-I Foundation to attend ISCLS 2019 (Kharagpur) and WSC 2023 (Online).
- Financial support under ACM SIGSOFT CAPS Virtual Program to attend ESEC/FSE 2021.
- Travel grants from ACM India to attend CoDS-COMAD 2017 (Goa), CoDS-COMAD 2018 (Kolkata) and CoDS-COMAD 2019 (Hyderabad).
- TCS Research Scholar Program Fellowship (Cycle 11), 2015.
- Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) Fellowship, given by Indian Institute of Sciences (IISc), 2007.
- National Talent Search (NTS) Scholarship, given by National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT), 2005.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages : Python, C, C++, Shell Scripting, Haskell, R, PHP, JavaScript, HTML, CSS

Databases : MySQL, Neo4j, MongoDB

Libraries : Flask, SQLAlchemy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Gensim, NLTK, spaCy, PyTorch, NumPy

Dev Tools : git, Python packaging, Make, docker **Typesetting** : LaTeX, Markdown, reStructuredText

PROJECTS

120+ \$\frac{1}{2}\$ 40+ **3** 2800+ **GitHub Profile Statistics** hrishikeshrt **PyPI Profile** hrishikeshrt

Sanskrit Language Model

ongoing

• Train language models for Sanskrit using a large corpus

Antarlekhaka Antarlekhaka/code

- Annotation of a comprehensive set of computational linguistic tasks.
- · General purpose, multi-task, sequential annotation.

Sangrahaka nrishikeshrt/sangrahaka

- · Annotation towards creation of knowledge graphs.
- · Querying of knowledge graphs using natural language query templates.

Jnanasangraha

https://sanskrit.iitk.ac.in/jnanasangraha

Collection of several web-based Sanskrit computational tools.

• Includes three of ancient Indian alpha-syllabic numeral systems, a Sankrit prosodical meter identification and utilization system and various utility functions related to Sanskrit alphabet.

Vaiyyakarana vyakarana_bot

• Telegram bot for the learners of Sanskrit grammar.

Sanskrit Audio Alignment

https://hrishikeshrt.github.io/audio_alignment

Interface for Sanskrit corpus recitation using forced-alignment to align text and audio.

EXTRACURRICULAR

- I like to provide support to students who require academic assistance and have volunteered as an academic mentor at CSE, IIT Kanpur.
- I am a frequent blood donor with 44 donations so far and actively promote blood donation. I have also served as the Overall Co-ordinator and PG Wing Head of Raktarpan, IIT Kanpur and helped organize more than 20 blood donation camps in and around campus.
- · I am interested in Sanskrit language and grammar. I hold a Diploma in Sanskrit Language under the Non-Formal Sanskrit Education programme offered by Central Sanskrit University. I have also completed Kovida, an advanced-level correspondence course offered by Samskrita Bharati.
- I love bicycling and have completed multiple 50km and 100km rides.

REFERENCES

Arnab Bhattacharya

arnabb@iitk.ac.in, arnabb@cse.iitk.ac.in

+91-512-259-7650

Professor, Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur ★ https://cse.iitk.ac.in/users/arnabb/

Pawan Goyal Associate Professor, Indian Institute of Technology Kharagpur

★ https://cse.iitkgp.ac.in/~pawang/

Professor, University of Hyderabad

pawang@cse.iitkgp.ac.in

+91-3222-282370

Amba Kulkarni

■ apksh@uohyd.ernet.in, ambapradeep@gmail.com

+91-40-23133800

A https://sanskrit.uohyd.ac.in/faculty/amba/

Piyush Rai Associate Professor, Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur

★ https://cse.iitk.ac.in/users/piyush/

+91-512-259-6894